# **Dong Ma** | Curriculum Vitae

15 JJ Thomson Ave, William Gate Building, Cambridge, UK, CB3 0FD

 $\square$  +44 07422527071 •  $\square$  E-mail: dm878@cam.ac.uk

♦ Homepage: https://madongxx.wixsite.com/dongma

### **Research Interests**

My research interests rotate around cyber-physical systems, including ubiquitous computing, pervasive sensing, vibration communication, energy harvesting, and mobile and wearable healthcare, covering the ene-to-end system design, implementation, and evaluation. Recently, I am particularly centred on robust human behaviour analysis and health monitoring with wearable technology and tiny machining learning on embedded devices.

### **Education**

Ph.D.

University of New South Wales, Australia

Computer Science and Engineering,

2016/10-2019/11

Advisor: Prof. Mahbub Hassan and Prof. Wen Hu

M.Sc.

Central South University, China

Information and Communication Engineering

2014/09-2016/06

Advisor: Prof. Jun Peng

B.Eng.

Central South University, China

2010/09–2014/06

Advisor: Prof. Xiaoheng Deng

Communication Engineering

# Research Experience

### Research Associate

2020/01-Present

Mobile System Group, University of Cambridge,

**Concentrations**: working on an ERC advanced project - 'Audio-based Mobile Health Diagnostics (EAR)', with particular focus on developing in-ear microphone based wearable systems for human signs (e.g., heartbeat, breathing, dietary activities, motions, gestures) detection and monitoring.

Research Assistant

2016/10-2019/11

Networked Systems and Security Group, University of New South Wales,

**Concentrations**: energy-efficient human activity/gesture/gait recognition using energy harvesters (e.g., kinetic energy harvester and solar cell)

Research Assistant 2017/01–2019/11

Networks Research Group, DATA61, CSIRO,

Concentrations: vibration communication over human skin

Research Assistant 2014/09–2016/06

Rail Transit Network Communication and Control Laboratory, Central South University,

Concentrations: device-to-device communication

### **Honors and Awards**

- o EPFL Engineering Ph.D. Summit, Switzerland, 2019. (1/11 worldwide)
- o Google Ph.D. Fellowship Nominee, Australia, 2019. (1/2 from University of New South Wales)
- o Student Travel Grant, ACM MobiCom 2018.
- o Best Demo Runner-up, ACM/IEEE IoTDI 2018.
- o DATA61 & CSIRO Top-up Scholarship, Australia, 2016 2020.
- o University International Postgraduate Award, University of New South Wales, 2016-2020.
- Outstanding Graduate, Central South University, 2014.
- o National Scholarship of China, 2013.

### **Publications**

Publication list also available at Google Scholar.

#### lournals

- \* indicates co-primary authors, † indicates corresponding author.
- o [1] **Dong Ma**, Guohao Lan, Changshuo Hu, Mahbub Hassan, Wen Hu, Mushfika Baishakhi Upama, Ashraf Uddin, and Moustafa Youssef. "Recognizing Hand Gestures using Solar Cells," *IEEE Transaction on Mobile Computing* (**TMC**), 2021. (**Under Review**)
- o [2] **Dong Ma**, Guohao Lan, Weitao Xu, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "Simultaneous Energy Harvesting and Gait Recognition using Piezoelectric Energy Harvester," *IEEE Transaction on Mobile Computing* (TMC), 2020. (IF=5.11) (PDF)
- o [3] **Dong Ma**<sup>†</sup>, Guohao Lan, Mahbub Hassan, Wen Hu, and Sajal K. Das. "Sensing, Computing, and Communication for Energy Harvesting IoTs: A Survey," *IEEE Communications Surveys & Tutorials* (COMST), 2019. (IF=29.83) (PDF)
- [4] Guohao Lan, Dong Ma<sup>†</sup>, Weitao Xu, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "Capacitor Based Activity Sensing for Kinetic Powered Wearable IoTs," ACM Transactions on Internet of Things (TIOT), 2019. (PDF)
- [5] Guohao Lan, Weitao Xu, Dong Ma, Sara Khalifa, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "EnTrans: Leveraging Energy Harvesting Signal for Transportation Mode Detection," *IEEE Transactions* on Intelligent Transportation Systems (TITS), 2014. (IF=5.74) (PDF)

## Conference Proceedings

- [6] Dong Ma\*, Andrea Ferlini\*, Robert Harle, and Cecilia Mascolo. "EarGate: Gait-based User Authentication with Earables," The 27th Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom), 2021. (Under Review)
- [7] Dong Ma, Andrea Ferlini, and Cecilia Mascolo. "OESense: Employing Occlusion Effect for In-ear Human Sensing," The 19th ACM International Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications, and Services (MobiSys), 2021. (Accepted) (PDF) (Dataset)
- [8] Dong Ma, Yuezhong Wu, Ming Ding, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "Skin-MIMO: Vibration-based MIMO Communication over Human Skin," *IEEE International Conference on Computer Communications* (INFOCOM), 2020. (Acceptance Rate: 19.8%) (PDF)
- [9] Changshuo Hu, Dong Ma, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "NLC: Natural Light Communication using Switchable Glass," *IEEE Workshop on Pervasive Systems in the IoT era* (Persist-IoT, INFOCOM Workshop), 2020. (PDF)
- o [10] Bo Wei, Weitao Xu, Chengwen Luo, Guillaume Zoppi, **Dong Ma**, and Sen Wang. "SolarSLAM: Battery-free Loop Closure for Indoor Localisation," *In the Proceedings of the 2020 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems* (IROS), 2020. (PDF)
- [11] Dong Ma, Ming Ding, and Mahbub Hassan. "Enhancing Cellular Communications for UAVs via Intelligent Reflective Surface," *IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference* (WCNC), 2020.(PDF)
- [12] Dong Ma, Guohao Lan, Mahbub Hassan, Wen Hu, Mushfika Baishakhi Upama, Ashraf Uddin, and Moustafa Youssef. "SolarGest: Ubiquitous and Battery-free Gesture Recognition using Solar Cells," The 25th Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom), 2019. (Acceptance Rate: 19%) (Simulator code at Github)(PDF)
- o [13] **Dong Ma**, Guohao Lan, Mahbub Hassan, Wen Hu, Mushfika Baishakhi Upama, Ashraf Uddin, and Moustafa Youssef. "Gesture Recognition with Transparent Solar Cells: A Feasibility Study," *The 12th ACM International Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Evaluation & Characterization* (WiNTECH, MobiCom Workshop), 2018. (PDF)
- [14] Dong Ma, Guohao Lan, Weitao Xu, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "SEHS: Simultaneous Energy Harvesting and Sensing using Piezoelectric Energy Harvester," The 3rd ACM/IEEE International Conference on Internet-of-Things Design and Implementation (IoTDI), 2018. (Acceptance Rate: 23%) (PDF)
- [15] Guohao Lan, Dong Ma, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "HiddenCode: Hidden Acoustic Signal Capture with Vibration Energy Harvesting," The 16th IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom), 2018. (Acceptance Rate: 13%) (PDF)

- [16] Guohao Lan, Dong Ma, Weitao Xu, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "CapSense: Capacitor-based Activity Sensing for Kinetic Energy Harvesting Powered Wearable Devices," Proceedings of the 14th EAI International Conference on Mobile and Ubiquitous Systems (MobiQuitous), 2017. (PDF)
- [17] Dong Ma, Jun Peng, Heng Li, Weirong Liu, Zhiwu Huang, and Xiaoyong Zhang. "Energy Efficient Video Streaming over Wireless Networks with Mobile-to-mobile Cooperation," *IEEE* Pacific Rim Conference on Communications, Computers and Signal Processing (PACRIM), 2015. (PDF)

### Poster & Demo.....

- [18] Changshuo Hu, Dong Ma, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "Poster: Data Communication using Switchable Privacy Glass," The 19th ACM/IEEE Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks (IPSN), 2020.
- o [19] **Dong Ma**, Guohao Lan, Weitao Xu, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "Demo Abstract: Simultaneous Energy Harvesting and Sensing using Piezoelectric Energy Harvester," *The 3rd ACM/IEEE International Conference on Internet-of-Things Design and Implementation* (IoTDI), 2018. (Best Demo Runner-up Award)
- o [20] **Dong Ma**, Guohao Lan, Weitao Xu, Mahbub Hassan, and Wen Hu. "Poster: Unobtrusive User Verification using Piezoelectric Energy Harvesting," *Proceedings of the 14th EAI International Conference on Mobile and Ubiquitous Systems* (MobiQuitous), 2017.

# **Teaching Experience**

### Supervisor for Part II, and MPhil Projects

2020 Term 3, 2021 Term 1

Department of Computer Technology, University of Cambridge,

**Role:** supervising research-oriented projects including (1) investigating accurate and efficient detection of teeth clenching through in-ear wearables, (2) wind noise removal for robust human speech acquisition.

### **Supervisor for Mobile Sensor Systems**

2021 Term 1

Department of Computer Science and Technology, University of Cambridge,

Role: supervising course tutorials

### **Head Tutor for Mobile Data Networking**

2018 Term 2, 2019 Term 2

School of Computer Science & Engineering, UNSW,

Role: tutoring lab tutorials and final assignment, marking

### Tutor for Internet of Things Experimental Design Studio

2018 Term 2

School of Computer Science & Engineering, UNSW,

Role: tutoring lab tutorials

# **Professional Activities**

### **Editorial Service:**

- o Program Committee Member at Earcomp 2021
- o Topic Editor of 'Al-Powered Smart Healthcare in Smart Cities' at Frontiers in Sustainable Cities

### **Review Service:**

- o 2021: IEEE TMC, TPDS, TII, MASS, ACM IMWUT
- o 2020: IEEE JSAC, ACM IMWUT, IEEE ICC, IEEE Comnets
- o 2019: ACM SenSys, ACM/IEEE IPSN, IEEE PerCom, IEEE IoTJ, IEEE WCNC, ACM SigGraph
- o 2018: ACM SenSys, IEEE ICDCS, IEEE PerCom, IEEE ICCCN, EAI Mobiguitous

# **Presentations and Talks**

- Keynote: OESense: Employing Occlusion Effect for In-ear Human Sensing, Research Students Symposium at University of Cambridge, May 2021, Online
- Talk: Activity Recognition Through In-ear Microphone Sensing, Mini Workshop at Nokia Bell Lab, May 2021, Online
- Conference Presentation: Skin-MIMO: Vibration-based MIMO Communication over Human Skin, INFOCOM, July 2020, Online
- Conference Presentation: Enhancing Cellular Communications for UAVs via Intelligent Reflective Surface, WCNC, May 2020, Online
- Conference Presentation: Enhancing Cellular Communications for UAVs via Intelligent Reflective Surface, MobiCom, October 2019, Los Cabos, Mexico
- Talk: Transformative Context Sensing for Energy Harvesting IoTs, EPFL Engineering PhD Summit, October 2019, Lausanne, Switzerland
- Conference Presentation: Gesture Recognition with Transparent Solar Cells: A Feasibility Study, WiNTECH, MobiCom Workshop, November 2018, New Delhi, India
- Conference Presentation: SEHS: Simultaneous Energy Harvesting and Sensing using Piezoelectric Energy Harvester, *IoTDI*, April 2018, Orlando, USA
- o **Conference Presentation**: CapSense: Capacitor-based Activity Sensing for Kinetic Energy Harvesting Powered Wearable Devices, *MobiQuitous*, November 2017, Melbourne, Australia